<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sacred rite of confirmation discoursed of in a sermon preach'd at Okeham in the county of Rutland at a confirmation there administred ... on May 17, 1683 / by John Savage ...</title>
            <author>Savage, J. (John), 1645-1721.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S770</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34219</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14147886</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14147886</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102105</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62257)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102105)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1069:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sacred rite of confirmation discoursed of in a sermon preach'd at Okeham in the county of Rutland at a confirmation there administred ... on May 17, 1683 / by John Savage ...</title>
                  <author>Savage, J. (John), 1645-1721.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. and F.C. for William Henseman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts VIII, 17 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102105:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102105:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Sacred Rite OF Confirmation.</p>
            <p>Diſcourſed of in a SERMON Preach'd at <hi>Okeham</hi> in the County of <hi>Rutland,</hi> At a Confirmation there Adminiſtred, by the Right Reverend Father in God <hi>WILLIAM</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>PETERBOROW.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>May</hi> 17. 1683.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Savage,</hi> Rector of <hi>Morcot</hi> in <hi>Rutland.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ACTS 15.41.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He went through <hi>Syria</hi> and <hi>Cilicia</hi> confirming the Churches</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>D. Hieron. Dial. adverſ. Luciferianos.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Si Scripture authoritas non ſubeſſet, totius Orbis in hanc partem conſenſus inſtar praecepti obtineret</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hookers Eccleſ. Polit. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 355.</bibl>
               <p>There is no cauſe we ſhould doubt of the benefit of Confirmation, but ſurely great cauſe to make complaint of the deep neglect of this Chriſtian Duty. Let Them not take it in evil part, the thing is true, their ſmall regard hereunto hath done harm to the Church of God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J.C.</hi> and <hi>F.C.</hi> for <hi>William Henſenian,</hi> at the <hi>Kings-head</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter-hall.</hi> 1683</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:102105:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102105:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend Father in God, WILLIAM Lord Biſhop of <hi>Peterborow.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Lordſhip,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN Obedience to your Lordſhips commands, I firſt Preacht, and now Publiſh this enſuing Diſcourſe. Whether I have offer'd any thing herein that may probably win any to a love of and veneration for this great Office, I ſhall not preſume to judge, none being more conſcious of its defects than my ſelf. But ſince it hath paſt your Lordſhips approbation, and was favourably receiv'd by the Reverend my Brethren of the Clergy, I do the leſs value the cenſures of others.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant that this Age, in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities and Cities eſpecially, abounds with great Scholars and eminent Preachers, the glory of our Church, as well as the envy of our Adverſaries; and I hope thoſe great men will not diſdain to have a Mite thrown in now and then (though by the meaneſt Rural Divine) to make ſome little addition to their Treaſury.</p>
            <p>When your Lordſhip firſt limited me to this ſubject, I thought it a barren ſoyl, becauſe not commonly manag'd, but after a few thoughts ſpent upon i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and turning up ſome of the ſurface, I promiſed my ſelf it would prove (to ſpeak like a Countrey-Parſon) of the ſame nature with new broken up ground, which uſually yields a double Crop. I
<pb facs="tcp:102105:3"/>found the matter ſo copious, and the Office, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> reckons amongſt his ſix Fundamentals, ſo eaſily defenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that it has run this Diſcourſe into a more than uſual length; for which I hope the great uſefulneſs of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, though not the way of handling it, will apologize, if not make ſufficient amends.</p>
            <p>That your Lordſhip hath highly advanced the honour and intereſt of this Church in general, and particularly retriev'd the almoſt loſt Reputation of this Sacred Office, ſtopping for ever the mouths of our Adverſaries (who are apt to bellow againſt unpreaching Biſhops, and the neglect of thoſe Offices that bring no ſecular advantage) by your frequent Preachings, publick Exhortations, and conſtant Miniſtration of this holy Office; That by your candour and condeſcenſion, you oblige your Clergy to a regular Conformity, and a love to your Lordſhips injunctions as well as perſon; That by force of Argument, manag'd with a winning mildneſs and ſweetneſs of diſpoſition, you have worn off the natural ruggedneſs of many of the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and prevail'd upon them to promiſe a ſubmiſſion: Theſe things are not unknown to us who have the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to live within your Juriſdiction, nor will it be deem'd a piece of Sycophantry by any who have the leaſt knowledge of your Lordſhips Perſon or Actions.</p>
            <p>And amongſt the many demonſtrations of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips known candour, theſe are not the leaſt, That you com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand me to Print this enſuing Diſcourſe, thereby ſhewing your readineſs to encourage the induſtry of the meaneſt; That you pleaſe to undertake the protection of it from the proud and cenſorious; And that you give me leave in ſo publick a manner to ſubſcribe my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble and Obedient Son and Servant, <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102105:3"/>
            <head>The TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Acts 8. Chap. 17. v.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Then laid they their hands on them, and they received the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SAint <hi>Luke</hi> having in his Goſpel given an account of the Actions and Sayings of our bleſſed Saviour, from the time of his Birth, till his Aſcenſion into Heaven, (which glorious <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> of his we do this day com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate, and whoſe <hi>gifts</hi> ſoon after beſtow'd are on this day to be diſtributed) does in this Sacred Hiſtory inform us of ſome of the moſt remarkable paſſages in the Lives of the Holy Apoſtles. Whereof ſome are common unto all, others peculiar to a few: thoſe that are peculiar, he reſtrains eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the one of the Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the other the Apoſtle of the Uncircumciſion; and by reſtraining his Hiſtory to theſe two, he does tacitly inſinuate, that the reſt of the Apoſtles were no leſs induſtrious in their ſeveral Provinces to propagate the Goſpel of Chriſt. Amongſt thoſe actions that are common unto them all, none more properly relates to the occaſion of this preſent Solemnity, than that remarkable Office of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> here recorded in the Text, which the Apoſtles by St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>John,</hi> their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Delegates, did adminiſter to a numerous company of the baptized <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                     <desc>•••…</desc>
                  </gap>aritans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For St. <hi>Stephen</hi> being Crowned with Martyrdom, <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. and a violent perſecution being rais'd againſt the Church, in the beginning of the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, the ſix ſurviving Deacons, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Chriſtian Profeſſors, were ſcattered abroad through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Regions of <hi>Judea</hi> and <hi>Samaria,</hi> preaching the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel of Chriſt. But the Apoſtles having not as yet compos'd the common Symbol of Faith, or having not by lot or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage aſſign'd to themſelves their ſeveral Provinces, continued ſtill at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where they ſoon received the joyful news
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102105:4"/>of that wonderful ſucceſs the Goſpel of Chriſt had obtained by the preaching of St. <hi>Philip</hi> the Deacon, who by Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical aſſignment, as ſome, or by Divine impulſe, as others, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Sebaſte,</hi> a Town founded by <hi>Herod</hi> the great to the honour of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and the Metropolitan City of <hi>Samaria,</hi> verſe the fifth, reſcu'd that whole City from the inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer, and converted them to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity: for though <hi>all from the leaſt to the greateſt had given heed unto Simon, ſaying, This man is the great power of God,</hi> v. 10. yet when <hi>they believed Philip preaching the things concerning the Kingdom of God, and the Name of Jeſus Chriſt, they were Baptized both men and women,</hi> v. 12. and thoſe were the people <hi>with one accord,</hi> v. 6. The news whereof coming to the Colledge of the Apoſtles, then reſiding at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they unanimouſly ſent <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to compleat and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect by their Apoſtolical Authority what was ſo happily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun by <hi>Philip</hi> the Deacon, v. 14. who being come to <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> and <hi>praying for them that they might receive the holy Ghoſt,</hi> (and that in a more eminent and abundant meaſure than they had at their Baptiſm) v. 15. their holy and ſervent prayers met with a ſuitable return, this Sacred Hiſtorian aſſuring us in the words of the Text, <hi>That having then laid their hands on them, they received the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what was then done by the Apoſtles in their own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, we are now met together by the good providence of God, to ſee in ſome meaſure perform'd by one of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Succeſſors, who though he pretends not by vertue of his Succeſſion to the ſame power the Apoſtles were endowed with, <hi>viz.</hi> Of conveying the gift of working Miracles, and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with unknown Tongues, thoſe gifts, together with their neceſſity in the infancy of the Church, having long ſince cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; yet may juſtly challenge from thoſe his Predeceſſors, all that power that is now neceſſary and eſſential to the edifying and governing of a well-conſtituted Church, part of which does conſiſt in this holy Rite of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> which he is now about to adminiſter to all that are duely qualified; and I hope All are ſo, (through the care and induſtry of their ſeveral Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors) that are here met this day with an intention to receive this holy Myſtery. And the greater grounds we have to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102105:4"/>hope it, when we conſider how many thouſands in this little County, beyond the uſual number, were prevail'd upon and prepar'd for receiving the holy Euchariſt at <hi>Eaſter</hi> laſt; in which, bleſſed be God, we had almoſt as wonderful a ſucceſs as St. <hi>Philip</hi> had in that City of <hi>Samaria,</hi> whole ſhoals and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of people, (the moſt inveterate of Rebels and Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not excepted) throwing off thoſe Sorceries and Enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherewith they had lately been deluded, and coming with at leaſt an outward Reverence and Devotion to that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacrament.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, we the Officers of our Lord, in purſuance of our original Commiſſion, and the late Orders to us directed, were forc'd to go into the <hi>high-ways and hedges,</hi> to <hi>compel</hi> ſome ſtraglers to come in, that theſe his Conſecrated Houſes might be <hi>filled;</hi> but when we came unto them, we found it was their diſuſe and ignorance of the thing that created a preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice; for when they ſubmitted to the Summons, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the decorum and gravity us'd in the celebrating of thoſe holy myſteries, their fear of the Laws was preſently chang'd into a love for their duty; and their ſeeming alacrity and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, makes us almoſt to think that Proctors and Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riters will be altogether as uſeleſs now, as they were in the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where the Diſciples <hi>continued with one accord in the Temple.</hi> Guardians of Churches, without the guilt of Perjury, may ſhortly make their preſentments <hi>Omnia bene;</hi> Canons and Conſtitutions may hereafter be made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the neceſſity of affixing <hi>Anathema's;</hi> and we ſhall again recover the golden age, where <hi>be that runs will read</hi> his duty, and every one will be Religious without the force of Coercive Laws.</p>
            <p>Theſe good Succeſſes and happy Omens we muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge due (under God) to the care and vigilance of our right Reverend Dioceſan, by which in ſome competent meaſure, as far as his Sphere reaches, he hath ſecur'd unto us the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this preſent Age. But his care for us is not here ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated; that he might derive the like Piety and Devotion to Poſterity, and the ſucceeding Ages might ſhare with us in the happy influences of his wiſe government, he did by the like Orders lately enjoyn his Clergy to prepare the younger
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102105:5"/>ſort by Catechizing and wholſome Inſtructions for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy partaking of this holy Ordinance. And thanks be to God, we do this day ſee the joyful fruits of our labours: we have indeed heretofore toyl'd day and night, and have caught little or nothing; but when by the aſſiſtance of our Saviour, and the direction of ſo wiſe a Pilot, we threw out our net, behold what a vaſt multitude is here encompaſſed, both ſmall and great! and though the draught be ſo large, we need no Trimmers to ſecore our veſſel; it will neither ſink with its own weight, nor will the waves of this world prevail a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, if to a lively faith in Chriſt we adde a reciprocal love amongſt our ſelves, and unanimouſly reſolve to carry on what is thus ſo happily begun.</p>
            <p>And that I according to my model may make one ſtep to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the carrying on of this great work, and the meaneſt in the Auditory may underſtand the nature of this great Office that is now about to be celebrated, let me humbly crave your attention whilſt I inſiſt on this remarkable inſtance, which the Apoſtles have here given us, a ſummary account whereof we have in the words of the Text:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then laid they their hands on them, and they received the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words afford us theſe two Generals.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The celebration of a holy Rite or Ceremony: <hi>Then laid they their hands on them.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The wonderful effects or conſequents of it: <hi>And they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In treating of the firſt General, I ſhall briefly diſcourſe of theſe following things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Of this Ceremony in general, ſhewing you the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it.</item>
               <item>2. Of the nature of this particular Ceremony, what it is ſignificative of, the great ends and purpoſes for which it was originally uſed, and afterwards inſtituted and practiſed in the Chriſtian Church; together with the material duty that this Ceremony did heretofore wait upon and accompany; and from thence the expediency of it will be diſcemed.</item>
               <item>3. I ſhall diſcover to you that peculiar Order of perſons to whom the adminiſtration of this holy Office is reſtrained,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102105:5"/>with ſome probable Reaſons of ſuch reſtriction; and from thence we ſhall ſee the honour and veneration we ought to have for it; not ſo much in it ſelf conſidered, but as it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>next to the higheſt Order in the Church, the Apoſtles and the ſucceeding Biſhops.</item>
               <item>4. I ſhall lay down the qualifications of thoſe to whom this Office is to be adminiſtred; and from thence the holineſs of it will appear, it being not promiſcuouſly to be adminiſtred to all that ſhall rudely and unpreparedly offer themſelves, but ſet apart for, and appropriated to ſober and competently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent Chriſtians.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In treating of the ſecond General, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew,
<list>
                  <item>1. What were the great and ſtupendious effects of it upon its firſt inſtitution and practice.</item>
                  <item>2. That the conſequents of it now upon its preſent admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration by Epiſcopal, are altogether as valuable as thoſe were that enſu'd upon the impoſition of Apoſtolical hands.</item>
                  <item>3. That the ſeeming diſproportion betwixt the outward means and the inward effects, ought not to prejudice any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderative perſon againſt the power and efficacy thereof.</item>
                  <item>4. We ſhall from the premiſed Poſitions eaſily infer the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and uſefulneſs of this holy Office, if not the neceſſity of its continuance in the Chriſtian Church: And ſo briefly conclude our diſcourſe with humble and modeſt Perſuaſives to all perſons concern'd.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt General,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Gen.</note> and under that with the firſt thing that offers it ſelf to our conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">I. And that is to treat of this Ceremony in general. That impoſition of hands is a meer Ceremony, having nothing of intrinſick goodneſs to recommend its uſe u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                  <desc>••…</desc>
               </gap> us, is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by all; and yet this Ceremony (which abſtractedly conſider'd was neither good nor evil, which might have been done or left undone <hi>pro libitu,</hi> according to the pleaſure or diſcretion of its Authors, without any prejudice to the Church, or violation of any Chriſtian Law) was uſed by our Saviour upon ſeveral occaſions, and practiſed by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in this and many other inſtances. Now is it not much that our Saviour and his Apoſtles ſhould be ſo ceremonious, that they ſhould offer to practiſe that at which the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102105:6"/>of tender Chriſtians might probably be offended? what! had they no regard to the ſcruples that might poſſibly ariſe in the new converted <hi>Samaritans,</hi> or could they not foreſee what offences more enlightned Chriſtians in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages would take at ſuch legal worſhip, ſuch matters of indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferency in Gods ſervice? Neither of theſe can be imputable to our Saviour, and no doubt the Apoſtles had a juſt regard to the one, and by inſpiration or rational conjecture did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the other; but they well underſtood that not ſuch indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent things by them practiſed, but the indiſcretion of ſome and the malice of others would create thoſe prejudices; they might pity ſuch perſons as weak and wicked, but this was not reaſon ſufficient to deny the Service or Diſcipline of the Church its innocent and ſignificant Ceremonies, becauſe there are ſools or mad men that will either laugh or rayl at them.</p>
            <p>That God did actually reſtrain the natural liberty of man before the Law was delivered, nay before Circumciſion was enjoyn'd, is plain from many inſtances, particularly from ſome of thoſe ſeven precepts delivered by God to the Sons of <hi>Noah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9.4.</note> which in themſelves conſidered, are of an indifferent nature, and could not be eſteemed by the Heathen Proſelytes of <hi>Antioch</hi> to be what the Apoſtles called them, <hi>neceſſary things,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 15.28</note> had they not been made neceſſary to them by a former poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive inhibition, or at leaſt at that time become neceſſary in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the end they aimed at; the reſtraining our liberty in things indifferent being ſometimes abſolutely neceſſary, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the peace and unity of the Church.</p>
            <p>And as God before the Law did reſtrain mans liberty from ſeveral things indifferent; ſo when the Law was to be abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, our Saviour does however by a poſitive injunction tye us up to the obſervance of ſome indifferent things. Nay, he was ſo far from ſcrupling the uſe of lawful and innocent Rites, that he adopted two Jewiſh Ceremonies into the Chriſtian Doctrine; the one from Baptizing of Proſelytes, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the <hi>Poſtroenium</hi> of the Paſchal Lamb; neither of which was enjoyned by the Levitical Law,<note place="margin">St. Mat. 28.19. St. Mat. 26.26.</note> and yet both of them appointed by him as the laſting and perpetual Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Church. By his indiſpenſable enjoyning onely
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102105:6"/>theſe two, he did ſignifie his diſlike of that burthenſome va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety which the Law and the traditions of the Elders requir'd; but by appointing theſe two, he did alſo ſhew that it is not unlawful under the Goſpel to appoint Rites and Ceremonies, ſo they be for order and edification. And this our Saviour in many other inſtances did intimate unto us. By a word from his mouth he might have infus'd his holy Spirit into the hearts of his Apoſtles, but his infinite wiſdom rather made choice to joyn with it that ſignificant ceremony of <hi>breathing on them,</hi> thereby ſignifying,<note place="margin">St. John 20.22.</note> that he did at that inſtant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from himſelf convey the holy Ghoſt unto them. And to come cloſer to our preſent purpoſe; Had our Saviour been nice and ſcrupulous in ſuch matters of indifferency, the pronouncing his benediction on the children that were brought unto him had been ſufficient;<note place="margin">St. Mark 10.16.</note> he had never <hi>taken them up into his arms and laid his hands upon them,</hi> uſing Ceremonis bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenſome to himſelf, as well as offenſive to others.</p>
            <p>I need not inſtance in that famous Council celebrated at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the Apoſtles;<note place="margin">Acts 15.28.</note> nor need I recount the Apoſtles Canons collected by <hi>Clemens Romanus,</hi> even thoſe that are accounted genuine; wherein their Chriſtian as well as natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral liberty was reſtrain'd, and by which they conſulted not the cavils and petulant humours of Gainſayers, but the peace and ſafety of the Church. Let it ſuffice that holy Scriptures do abundantly teſtifie this to be the conſtant practice of the Apoſtles, when they thought it a good expedient for Peace or Decency: Thus we find St. <hi>Paul</hi> to make an order, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> but in <hi>Corinth</hi> too,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.1.</note> 
               <hi>that on the firſt day of the week collections ſhould be made for the neceſſitous Saints at Jeruſalem.</hi> Now the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were generally rich, and (not unlikely) ſawcy and conceited, as appears from the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and thoſe two genuine ones of the aforeſaid <hi>Clemens;</hi> and ſuppoſe any of them had objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this order, that Chriſt had freed them from the Law of ordinances, that Months, and Years, and Days, were not now to be obſerv'd, that this ſubſtantial duty of charity might as well be performed on any other day as well as the firſt, and therefore their Chriſtian liberty ought not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded; what think ye would St. <hi>Paul</hi> have done in this caſe?
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102105:7"/>would he have receded from his Apoſtolical power, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified the malepert humours of a few of thoſe rich, but ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous <hi>Corinthians?</hi> undoubtedly he would not; for an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der being once made upon mature deliberation by lawful au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, if reſcinded upon no other conſideration, but becauſe every mans judgment cannot approve of, or every ones hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour will not comply with it, opens a door for all Faction and Schiſm, and quite unhinges the whole frame of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſurely would have viſited ſuch perſons with the <hi>rod,</hi> and not <hi>in the ſpirit of meekneſs;</hi> and have <hi>delivered them up unto Satan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.20. 2 Tim. 4.15.</note> as he did <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> for withſtanding his word.</p>
            <p>That common ſaying in the mouth of every late Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>viz.</hi> That God requireth the Heart of man, and not his Hat, St. <hi>Paul</hi> clearly proves to be a vulgar errour: for he tells us,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.4.</note> That <hi>every man praying or prophecying</hi> (which belongs to the people as well as the Prieſt) <hi>having his head covered, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth his head; i. e.</hi> by ſuch an irreverent poſture, (during the Office either of Praying or Preaching) diſhonoureth Chriſt;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.3</note> for Chriſt is the Head of man.</p>
            <p>When the Apoſtles had Manacles on their hands,<note place="margin">Acts 16.25.</note> and Fetters on their legs, 'tis likely they conſulted their own eaſe, in finding out fit poſtures for offering up their Prayers; but when thoſe impediments were removed, and the ſhackles thrown off, they <hi>bended their knees</hi> and <hi>lifted up their hands</hi> in their conſtant Devotions; this being agreeable to the pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern our Saviour had given them,<note place="margin">St. Luke 22.41. Acts 21.5. Eph. 3.14.</note> who in the garden <hi>kneeled down and prayed.</hi> Thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> entring into the Oratory on the ſea-ſhore, <hi>kneeled down and prayed.</hi> And <hi>for this cauſe how I my knees unto the God and Father, &amp;c.</hi> And he requires the Chriſtians to <hi>lift up holy hands without wrath or doubting.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.8.</note> So ceremonious were Chriſt and his Apoſtles, that they would not <hi>ſit</hi> when they could <hi>kneel;</hi> they would not irreverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lean upon their elbows, when they could lift up holy hands.</p>
            <p>Sitting or leaning (if that can be proved to have been the poſture) was well enough becoming the Apoſtles at the firſt inſtitution of the Lords Supper; Chriſt being then in the fleſh, in his ſtate of humiliation, and not requiring from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102105:7"/>them then, thoſe outward tokens of Divine Worſhip or Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: But now, being glorified as God, and challenging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyſance from Men and Angels, Holy Church for good reaſon hath changed that poſture of <hi>Leaning</hi> for this of <hi>Kneeling:</hi> For <hi>although we have known Chriſt after the fleſh,</hi> and leaning in his boſom might be the effect of his great condeſcention, yet ſeeing we <hi>know him ſo no more,</hi> ſeeing he hath declared himſelf to be <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the firſt and the laſt,<note place="margin">Rev. 1.8, 11.</note> 
               <hi>God bleſſed for ever;</hi> 'tis fit we ſhould change that familiar way of communicating with him; and leſt we ſhould be accounted <hi>Socinians</hi> (who uſe a Table-geſture, as not owning the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of our Saviour) with all humility upon our knees revere and adore, not the Conſecrated Elements, but the glorified Perſon of the Bleſſed Jeſus.</p>
            <p>But that we may ſpeak particularly to the inſtance that is here before us, the Apoſtles were not ſcrupulous to uſe this ceremony in the Text, although joyned with Prayer; a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial part of Divine Worſhip; nay, although it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> who from a Doctrine that our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had taught them, might be as much prejudiced againſt ſuch practices, as our lately nice and ſcrupulous Diſſenters. They might have objected after this manner; Did not your Maſter, in whoſe name ye teach, tell a woman of our City that <hi>God is a Spirit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">St. John 4.24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>and he that will worſhip him muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth?</hi> and do you his pretended Diſciples come into our City and act contrary to your Maſters Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? either renounce your pretended Diſcipleſhip, or lay aſide theſe childiſh and Superſtitious Ceremonies, which are ſo inconſiſtent with the worſhipping of God in Spirit and in Truth. 'Tis true, the <hi>Samaritans</hi> might have objected this, but we find they were wiſer than to do ſo; they well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that our Saviour in that ſaying of his, alluded to the Religion to which they had hitherto been addicted,<note place="margin">2 Kings 17.24, 26, 29.</note> a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of a mixt nature, conſiſting of Jewiſh Sacrifices, offered up not onely to the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but to Heathen Idols; and therefore ſhe hour would come when thoſe Jewiſh Sacrifices would be laid aſide, and God would be worſhipped with the ſpirits of men, and not with the bodies of Bulls and of Goats; and thoſe Heathen Idols which are vanity or a lye,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102105:8"/>muſt be daſht to pieces, and God who is the eternal truth muſt be worſhipped by them. This they knew to be our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours meaning, and that ſuch innocent ceremonies were no way inconſiſtens with that Spiritual worſhip he required.</p>
            <p>So that you ſee though theſe were babes in Chriſt, and as tenderly to be dealt with as new-born Infants, yet this cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony joyned with Prayer, as the Apoſtles would not wave it, ſo the <hi>Samaritans</hi> were wiſer than to be ſcandalized at it.</p>
            <p>This then being a plain and undeniable truth, that inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and ſignificant Ceremonies may lawfully be uſed in the Church of Chriſt, Proceed we to the ſecond thing.</p>
            <p n="2">II. To inquire into the nature of this particular Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, what it is ſignificative of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I need not tell you that the hand is the member or inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by which we beſtow our largeſſes, or convey our gifts and kindneſſes to others; nor that even Nature carries the Fathers hand towards the Childs head, although at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant he knows not how or why he does it, when he out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly prays for, or inwardly wiſhes him a bleſſing.</p>
            <p>The Eaſtern Heathens were not ſtrangers to this cuſtom; <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian</hi> being offended at the Prophet for direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to ſo unlikely a cure, as <hi>waſhing ſeven times in the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Jordan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Kings 5.9.</note> huffingly replyed, <hi>I thought he would ſurely come out to me and ſtand and call on the Name of the Lord his God,</hi> and ſtrike or lay his hands over the place, and recover the leper.</p>
            <p>And that this Ceremony long before the giving of the Law was uſually joyned with paternal benedictions, is plain from the Father of the Patriarchs,<note place="margin">Gen. 48.14.</note> who by prayer and <hi>impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands</hi> bleſſed the Sons of <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Under the Law the conſecration of things or perſons to the ſervice of God,<note place="margin">Num. 8.10.12.</note> was by Divine appointment to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by <hi>laying on of hands.</hi> So when <hi>Moſes</hi> made <hi>Joſhua</hi> partner with him in his Government, and conveyed to him the right of ſucceſſion,<note place="margin">Num. 27.18.</note> by Gods commandment he <hi>laid his hands upon him;</hi> by which he did not onely impart the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, but the more neceſſary qualifications of Majeſty; for by this he became <hi>full of the ſpirit of wiſdom, Moſes having laid his hands upon him,</hi> Deut. 34.9.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102105:8"/>
            <p>And as Bleſſings ſpiritual and temporal were convey'd by impoſition of hands under the Law; ſo our Saviour and his Apoſtles under the Goſpel thought good to retain that Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, when they recovered the Sick, when they abſolv'd the Penitents, when they bleſſed Infants, when they Confirm'd the Baptized, and when they ordain'd Prieſts and Deacons. To inſtance in each of theſe, would require more time than is here allotted; its own evidence makes it ſufficient that I hint unto you, that in all theſe ſeveral Offices, together with the ſubſtantial duty of Prayer, they made uſe of this very antient Ceremony; and that probably for theſe two Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To lignifie that at that time there were true and real (not airy or imaginary) Bleſſings convey'd to the partakers; for what can be more real than the Spirit of Wiſdom and godly Fear? what can be more real than Courage and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnaniimty ſufficient to conquer the World, and baffle the ſtrongeſt Enemies of mankind, as I ſhall have occaſion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to ſhew? and what could better ſignifie the real exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of theſe, than laying their Hands on them?</p>
            <p n="2">2. To ſignifie that the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Church were the ordinary Means and Inſtruments, the Hands which God makes uſe of to convey his Gifts and communicate his Bleſſings unto men. Such publick and ſolemn Offices as theſe, wherein extraordinary Bleſſings were invocated, as they were not rudely and nakedly to be adminiſtred without the decent attendance of ſome ſignificant Ceremonies, ſo neither were they to be perform'd nor the Bleſſings to be expected, without the miniſtration of conſecrated perſons. 'Tis their Office to attend us from our Birth to our Grave; by their hands we are regenerated in the <hi>laver of Baptiſm;</hi> by their hands we are abundantly ſtrengthened againſt all ſpiritual Enemies in <hi>Confirmation;</hi> from their hands we receive the holy <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> the benefits of our Saviours Death, and the I ledge of his eternal Love; from their hands, if we fall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the cenſures of the Church, we receive <hi>Abſolution;</hi> and from the laying on of their hands, together with the holy Chriſm (a cuſtom far different from what is now us'd in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) the Primitive Chriſtians were freed from their ſeveral bodily Diſtempers; or at leaſt from their hands
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102105:9"/>they then received the ſymbol of Chriſts Body and Bloud, as the laſt and eternal <hi>Viaticum</hi> of their Souls. I ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite in recounting unto you all the Bleſſings which God by theſe his Servants was and is pleaſed to communicate unto men, and that under this holy and ſignificant Rite of <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then, in this ſolemn Office of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> great and unſpeakable Bleſſings being to be convey'd, and thoſe by his ſuperiour Servants the principal Stewards of his Houſhold, what fitter and more ſignificant Rite could poſſibly be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd, whereby to ſecure a Bleſſing to the one, and Honour to the other, than that which the Light of Nature hath affixt to Paternal Benedictions, than what the holy Patriarchs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law did practiſe, than what under the Law in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral the like caſes was enjoyn'd, than what our Saviour did frequently uſe, and to conclude, than what humane Reaſon could not poſſibly invent any thing more plain and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant?</p>
            <p>But, will ſome ſay, Was this all that the Apoſtles uſed, and did the Bleſſings of God follow the Impoſition of Hands onely? No ſurely, there was ſomething elſe belong'd to this great Office, and that of a higher and more valuable nature in it ſelf, than what is here mentioned. We are told, <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. that the Apoſtles, when they were come to <hi>Samaria, prayed for them that they might receive the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Prayer is an eſſential part of the Divine Worſhip, but Impoſition of Hands is onely a decent and ſignificant Ceremony proper and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dapted to the preſent occaſion. Their ſervent and devout Prayers were the holy charms that invited the Spirit of God to deſcend from Heaven, but Impoſition of Hands muſt be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged onely as a decent Rite, made uſe of mainly to ſignifie that this Spirit would ordinarily come to none but by the mediation and miniſtry of thoſe whom he had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
            <p>'Tis very evident that Prayer was the main Duty; and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Hands the principal Ceremony; and this is All that we find here recorded concerning the nature of this holy Office: Where then ſhall we find the holy Chriſin conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Biſhop, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> calls the <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter?</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:102105:9"/>where ſtands recorded that jingling Sentence, <hi>Signo te ſigno crucis, &amp; confirmo te Chriſmate ſolutis, in nomine Patris, &amp;c.</hi> which they ſay is the <hi>Form</hi> of their pretended Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? If you will find them, you muſt ſearch Pope <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>'s Decretals to the <hi>Armenians,</hi> with the approbation of the Council of <hi>Florence;</hi> or if that will not ſatisfie, you may conſult the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and the Roman Catechiſm, which give a large and more plenary account of it: but let me advize you not to ſearch the Scriptures for it, for there you ſhall not find the leaſt tittle concerning it.</p>
            <p>And yet 'tis ſomewhat ſtrange the Scriptures ſhould be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in a buſineſs of ſuch importance; to record nothing but Prayer and Impoſition of Hands, and to paſs by the Matter and Form, the two eſſential parts of a Sacrament, ſeems to be an unpardonable omiſſion in thoſe holy Pen-men. But you will find the miſtake was not theirs; this Sacriledge or holy Cheat muſt be imputed to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly acknowledges that, <hi>Loco illius manus impoſitionis, datur in Eccleſiâ confirmatio; i. e.</hi> if we may be ſo bold as to render it into its true Engliſh, Prayer and Impoſition of Hands is juſtled out, and the holy Croſs, with ſanctified Balſam, and a kind of Charm at the end of it, is got into the Chair, and commenc'd a Sacrament. Had the Romaniſts retain'd Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Impoſition of Hands, not advancing it to the honour of a Sacrament, but honouring it as a Sacramental completion (which is as much as it will amount to) and added the Croſs and Oyl onely as decent and ſignificant Ceremonies to attend upon it, they had kept themſelves within the bounds of modeſty: for the truth is, Chriſm was of very ancient uſe even in this holy Office, together with the honourable badge of our Saviour's Croſs, as <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who lived in the latter end of the ſecond Century, teſtifies in his Tractate <hi>De réſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectione carnis. Caro abluitur, ut anima emaculetur: Caro un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur, ut anima conſecretur: Caro ſignatur, ut &amp; anima muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur: Caro manus impoſitione adumbratur, ut &amp; anima ſpiritis illuminetur: Caro corpore &amp; ſanguine Chriſti veſcitur, ut &amp; ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma de Deo ſaginetur.</hi> Where you ſee, betwixt the two Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments he gives us an account of Confirmation, and the three Ceremonies that did then attend upon it, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>ſigne
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:102105:10"/>of the Croſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> and <hi>Impoſition of Hands.</hi> And St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> about the middle of the third Century mentions the ſigne of the Croſs in this holy Office, in his Epiſtle to <hi>Jubaia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t per noſtram orationem ac manus impoſitionem ſpiritum ſanctum conſequantur, &amp; ſignaculo Dominico conſummentur.</hi> So that it muſt be confeſt that theſe Ceremonies were of ancient uſe in the Church; and had they been retain'd onely as ſuch, the more ſober ſort of Chriſtians 'tis likely would not have been offen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>: But for the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to lay aſide the Apoſtolical inſtitution, and to advance theſe extrinſick Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies to the ſame honour with the holy Euchariſt, is a far greater crime than ſhe committed in the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> where ſhe onely denies the Cup to the Laity, as reſolving to keep them ſober; but retains the uſe of both kinds to her proper Repreſentatives, their Prieſts ſtanding on tiptoe rather than leave the leaſt drop behind them.</p>
            <p>Here then you may plainly ſee the ignorance of ſome, and the impudence of others, who are Adverſaries to our Church. The ignorance (I will not ſay the malice) of our late Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, who alledg'd that this Office of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> as it is us'd in our Church, is a ſuperſtitious practice, and no better than a Tranſcript of the Popes Decretals; whereas if they are compar'd together, they are as oppoſite as light and dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; their old Maſter <hi>Cartwright,</hi> who firſt broacht this Scandal, openly retracting it upon better information. Here you may likewiſe behold the forehead of thoſe who pretend to pay a great reverence to Antiquity, who yet curtail one of the Sacraments with a <hi>Non obſtante,</hi> and to make amends for it, adde five more as of equal dignity. 'Twould be matter of wonder that theſe things ſhould gain ſo great a repute e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven amongſt the vulgar, were it not that we ſee intelligent Kings and Princes to be every day impos'd upon with the ſuppoſed holineſs of Toys and Trifles; for ſurely this new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coin'd Sacrament muſt be preſum'd to do as much good to the partakers of it (if there be no real Obſtacle to hinder its efficacy) as the <hi>Conſecrated Clouts</hi> (and Rattles) lately ſent from <hi>Rome</hi> to the Infant-Duke of <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to wave the levity of their Pretences, more fit for a Stage than a Pulpit, We of the Church of <hi>England</hi> retaining
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102105:10"/>the Primitive Inſtitution and practice, may comfortably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a Bleſſing upon this holy Office; here being no <hi>traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men</hi> impoſed upon us as the Commandments of Chriſt, no Prayers offered up upon this occaſion but what the Church upon mature deliberation hath compos'd; no Ceremonies, as eſſential to the Office being here uſed, but what the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles practiſed; and all this as heretofore adminiſtred by the Apoſtles, ſo now by the Biſhops their lawful Succeſſors. And this brings me to the third, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. The peculiar Order of perſons to whom the miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this holy Office is reſtrained. We find by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text, that although St. <hi>Philip</hi> converted them to Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and diſcipled them by the Sacrament of Baptiſm, yet this holy Office was perform'd by St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>John,</hi> v. 14. <hi>Now when the Apoſtles which were at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>heard that</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria <hi>had received the Word of God, they ſent</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> John. How! what is this that we hear? Was <hi>Peter</hi> ſent? were the Subjects ſo ſawcy and preſumptuous as to ſend their Prince on their Errand? Is not this He from whom his preſent Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs derives his Supremacy over all Dominions ſpiritual and temporal? Did not St. <hi>Peter</hi> underſtand his power, or was he ſo weak as ſneakingly to betray the Prerogative of his Chair? Or if he did for that time ſuffer himſelf, like the titular Duke of <hi>Venice,</hi> to be concluded in the general Vote, yet could not his <hi>Infallibility</hi> guide him in executing the Commiſſion? Muſt he have a Collegue appointed him to ſeture his Superiouts that all things ſhall be rightly perform'd? Behold then the ſandy Foundation upon which the Romaniſts erect a ſupreme and infallible Chair to his Holineſs. O the miſerable ſhifts that they make to avoid the force of this unhappy inſtance! And yet amongſt them all, that which is the moſt plauſible brings him to an equality with the reſt of the Chriſtian Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; for <hi>A Lapide</hi> tells us, that as the Father ſent the Son,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> Loc.</note> and the Father and Son together ſent the Holy Ghoſt, and yet all three equal in Glory and Authority; ſo St. <hi>Peter</hi> may be ſaid to be ſent by the reſt of the Apoſtles, <hi>non imperio,</hi> as he quotes <hi>Cajetan</hi> for it, <hi>ſed fraterua charitate &amp; impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, be it ſo, nay we may go far higher, and grant him to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102105:11"/>be what they ſay the ſixth general Council own'd him,<note place="margin">Conc. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantin. 3.</note> 
               <hi>viz. Primus Epiſcoporum,</hi> upon condition they will grant on the other ſide what the ſame Council plainly determines, <hi>viz. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t thronus Conſtantinopolitanus aequalia privilegia cum antiquae Romae throno obtineat.</hi> Let him have the honor of precedency, let him upon all occaſions be the Mouth of his Collegues, let him open and conclude general Councils, let him be what they pretend St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> owns, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Origo,</hi> the <hi>Principium,</hi> the <hi>Exordium unitatis,</hi> provided they will grant him to be what the ſame holy Father ſays St. <hi>Peter</hi> was, in his golden Tractate <hi>De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitato Eccleſiae,</hi> where after he has told us that Chriſt hath given <hi>Apoſtolis omnibus parem poteſtatem,</hi> he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently tells us, <hi>Hoe erant uti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> &amp; caeteri Apoſtoli quod fuit Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus, pari conſortio praediti &amp; bonoris &amp; poteſtatis;</hi> which <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galtias</hi> miſerably endeavours to evade, by granting an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Apoſtleſhip as to their perſons, but denying it to their Succeſſors; an Hypotheſis altogether as abſurd and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, as their pretended Donation from <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great. But though we may be ſo civil as to grant him to be <hi>major ſingulis,</hi> yet his being ſent by the reſt of the Apoſtles, clearly evinces him to be <hi>Minor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis;</hi> which though it be a great Soloeciſm in the Civil, yet is not ſo in the Eccleſiaſtical Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. St. <hi>Peter</hi> you ſee was concluded by the general ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frage, and ſo his Succeſſours ought to be, as the Councils of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi> have ſtrenuouſly aſſerted.</p>
            <p>Sent it ſeems theſe Apoſtles were, but what was the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of their Commiſſion? It was this, that by their Prayer and Impoſition of Hands the Holy Ghoſt might deſcend upon the baptized Samaritans.</p>
            <p>But what was the reaſon that St. <hi>Philip,</hi> a Miniſter of Gods Word, did not perform this Duty? He was their Father in Chriſt, and had begotten them to a lively Faith; he had renew'd their Spirits in the Laver of Baptiſm, and inſtructed them in the neceſſary Rudiments of Chriſtianity; 'tis much that he did not ſolemnize this Office amongſt them: Beſides, Regeneration is of a higher nature than Confirmation, and he that gave the greater, why did he not give the leſs?</p>
            <p>The reaſon is plain and evident, Becauſe St. <hi>Philip</hi> was a perſon modeſt and faithful, and would not preſume to act
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102105:11"/>beyond his Commiſſion; he knew that the Apoſtles had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd this holy Office to their own miniſtration; and for him to attempt it, would have been a ſin equal to that of the Sons of <hi>Korah,</hi> who invaded the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſays that his Holineſs by the ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude of his Apoſtolical Authority may make an inferiour Prieſt the Miniſter of this Sacrament. If ſo, 'tis much that St. <hi>Peter</hi> would give himſelf ſuch an unneceſſary trouble, that he would not take his eaſe at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and appoint St. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip</hi> his lawful Subſtitute, giving him a Legantine power, as they ſay Deacons are capable of: Why, it ſeems St. <hi>Philip</hi> was more modeſt than to ask it; or if he had, St. <hi>Peter</hi> was more prudent than to grant it. Some things the Apoſtles did abſolutely reſerve to themſelves and their Succeſſors, which we the inferiour Officers of the Church may not, muſt not pretend to; and amongſt them, this of Confirmation was one; and this St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> fully teſtifies in his forecited Epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle to <hi>Jubaianus,</hi> ſpeaking of theſe Samaritans, <hi>Quod deerat,</hi> ſays he, <hi>id à Petro &amp; Johanne factum eſt, ut oratione pro eis ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitâ, &amp; manu impoſitâ invoedretur, &amp; infunderetur ſpiritus ſanctus.</hi> And that this was reſerv'd to the Biſhops the Sons of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in his age, himſelf being a Metrapolitan Biſhop, can beſt inform us: <hi>Quod nunc quo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> apud nos geritur, ut qui in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiá baptizantur, Praepoſitis Eccleſiae offerantur, ut per noſtram orationem ac manus impoſitionem ſpiritum ſanctum conſequantur, &amp;c.</hi> And this the incomparable <hi>Hooker</hi> out of St. <hi>Jerom. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſus Luciſer,</hi> proves to have been the practice of the fourth Century; who though no great friend to the Epiſcopal Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, yet tells us, that the cuſtom of the Churches is,<note place="margin">Non abnuo hanc eſſe Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, &amp;c. <hi>Dial. Orth. &amp; Luciſ.</hi>
               </note> that the Biſhop ſhould go abroad, and impoſing his hands, pray for the gift of the Holy Ghoſt on them whom Presbyters and Deacons, far off in leſſer Cities, had already baptized.</p>
            <p>And for good reaſon did the Apoſtles reſtrain this to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their Succeſſours, when we conſider theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this did ſecure unto them the honour of their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical Chairs; for the ſafety of the Church depends much upon the dignity of its Superiours, the reſpect that is given to their perſons, the reverence that is paid to their functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102105:12"/>Whereas if the chief Governours of the Church ſhall communicate to inferiour Orders their whole power, reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing by way of pre-eminence to themſelves to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh them from others; their power being thus made cheap, will become vile and deſpicable; the Hierarchy that Chriſt hath eſtabliſhed in his Church will ſoon be deſtroyed, their Offices confounded, and that queſtion of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.29. <hi>Are all Apoſtles, are all Prophets, are all teachers?</hi> would be anſwered in the affirmative: and to be ſhort, ſuch a levelling of all Sacred Orders, would be the undoubted pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of multiplied Factions and Schiſms. And though it may be objected that Confirmation is not of equal value with either of the Sacraments, both which inferiour Prieſts are capable of adminiſtring; yet it is by its reſtraint alone, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to ſecure the honour of the Function: for though a Velvet coat be of far greater worth than a plain linnen coif,<note place="margin">Hook. Ec. Pol. lib. 5. p. 355.</note> and the firſt may be worn by every common Lawyer, yet the ſecond being appropriated to Sergeants and Judges, procures them a reſpect due to their place and dignity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From hence the Apoſtles to whom the chief care of the Church was committed, were fully ſatisfyed as to the diligence and induſtry of the inferiour Officers whom they had depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. When they ſhould ſee 'em bring in full ſhoals and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Baptized Converts, offering up ſolemnly to God ſuch fruits of their labours, and preſenting them to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles for their Fatherly Prayers and Benedictions, this could not but be a ſufficient teſtimonial of their pains and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and by this the Apoſtles viſited the Clergy, exacting an account of their labours, as well as confirmed the Laity. And indeed no Society can be of long continuance, where there is not ſuch a due ſubordination; an Independency in the Church looſes the bands, and weakens the ſinews of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. That Congregation wherein every Prieſt is a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and every Biſhop a King, cannot be long without Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny: and that Aſſembly whoſe Members are ſuperiour to the Paſtor, and uncontrolable, cannot be long without Schiſm and Anarchy. But bleſſed be God, it was far otherwiſe in the Apoſtles times, and once again we ſee it otherwiſe in this our eſtabliſhed Church; where the members of it in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102105:12"/>matters of Religion and Conſcience are to be directed by their ſeveral Paſtors; the Presbyters and Deacons owning themſelves accountable for it to the Biſhop, the Biſhop to his Metropolitan, the Metropolitans to the King, and the King unto God. And when all theſe in their ſeveral ſpheres ſhall do nothing that they are afraid or aſhamed ſhould come to their Superiours cognizance, but rather be forward to give an account of their ſtewardſhips when required; this is the way to preſerve the Church in its honour and unity: We of the inferiour Clergy giving demonſtrations of our pains and induſtry, and our Superiours the Prelates and Fathers of the Church, reaping the comfort of ſeeing their Orders obeyed by a regular and induſtrious Clergy.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What a great comfort and ſatisfaction muſt needs ariſe to the Apoſtles, when they ſaw by the induſtry of others whom they had deputed, ſo great a part of their own bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then diſcharg'd, the ſeed of the Goſpel growing up and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in ſuch tender plants; the great myſteries of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on imbib'd by all ſorts of people, young and old, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſo great a number of Samaritan-converts, owning them not only as Miniſters of Chriſt, but as the principal Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of the Myſteries of God! What an opportunity was here offer'd them of glorifying of God, whoſe praiſe they found in the mouths of ſuch Infant-Converts The unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able comfort which they foreſaw would ariſe from ſo grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful an object; might probably induce them to reſerve this Office of Confirmation to themſelves and their Succeſſors; which though of an inferiour nature to Baptiſm, yet well becomes the higheſt Order in the Church; for hereby they do not onely own and ratifie the proceedings of thoſe whom they have deputed, ſetting their hands to the legality of it, which you know is the proper act of a Superiour; but they alſo confirm the Proſelytes in their lately received Faith, provided themſelves ſet no bar to hinder it. And this brings me to the fourth thing, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. The qualifications of thoſe to whom this Office is to be adminiſtred, which are theſe that follow.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be ſuppoſed that they are already made Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples by Baptiſm, and that by perſons lawfully ordained and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102105:13"/>appointed thereunto by the Apoſtles or their Succeſſors, as we find the <hi>Samaritans</hi> here were by St. <hi>Philip</hi> the Deacon; and therefore (according to my preſent apprehenſion) thoſe who have received their Baptiſm from Lay-hands, who cannot pretend to ſuch a derived power, are not qualified for this holy Rite, unleſs perform'd in a time of abſolute Neceſſity: And as for thoſe who have received their Baptiſm from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons lawfully ordained, but ſuch as by Schiſm or Hereſie are profeſſed enemies to our Church; I will not ſay that Rebap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tization is neceſſary, leſt I ſhould ſeem to fall into the errour of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and his <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Council; but that it is highly neceſſary for ſuch to addreſs themſelves to this holy myſtery, that by <hi>impoſition of hands</hi> they may be incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Church; and deſiring the Biſhops paternal bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, acknowledge his ſuperiority over them. That this is highly reaſonable in it ſelf, and agreeable to the practice of the Primitive Church, I need not prove to any one that has a competent ſhare of Reaſon, or the leaſt acquaintance with Antiquity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt be preſumed that either before or after Baptiſm they are endowed with actual Faith in Chriſt: before Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, if they were adult perſons; or after Baptiſm, if they were Infants at the miniſtring of it. A general faith before Baptiſm was ſufficient at the firſt planting of the Goſpel; the belief <hi>that Jeſus Chriſt was the Son of God</hi> was enough to entitle them to Baptiſm: but when Churches were well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, great care was taken to inſtruct the adult Proſelytes in all the Chriſtian Fundamentals; ſuch were the <hi>Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> of old; and both them and the Baptized Chriſtians were fully inſtructed in all neceſſaries of Faith, before they were preſented to the Biſhop for Confirmation; as appears from the fore-cited Dialogue of St. <hi>Jerom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dial. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod. &amp; Lucifer.</note> and from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition <hi>Irenaeus</hi> gives of the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2. where he interprets the <hi>Milk</hi> with which he had fed ſome of the Baptized <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> to be the <hi>firſt principles of Chriſtianity;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iren. lib. 5. cap. 75.</note> and the <hi>holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> obtained by <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>impoſition of hands,</hi> to be the <hi>Eſca vitae,</hi> the <hi>ſtronger food</hi> or meat of life; of which as yet they were uncapable, <hi>Quoniam infirmum adhuc &amp; inexercitabilem ſenſum erga Deum converſationis habebant.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:102105:13"/>
            <p n="3">3. It muſt be preſumed that they do not onely competently underſtand the Fundamentals of Faith, the rule of their Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and the nature of their Baptiſmal vow, with all other things of abſolute neceſſity, but that they here make an open profeſſion of them, publickly owning their Faith to be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, and their renunciation of all Spiritual Enemies ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, their Vows and Reſolutions fixt and permanent; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly renewing that promiſe that was made in their name at their Baptiſm,<note place="margin">Rubrick of Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
               <hi>ratifying and confirming the ſame in their own perſons,</hi> diſcharging their Sponſors, their Godfathers and Godmothers, from their former obligations, and <hi>acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves bound to believe and to do all thoſe things which they undertook for them.</hi> And all this is ſuppoſed to be done in the preſence of God and his holy Angels; the Biſhop be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here as our Saviours Repreſentative,<note place="margin">Ep. ad Saym <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ep. ad Teall. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> (for ſo <hi>Ignatius</hi> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtiles him) and taking from each of them their ſeveral fealties and acknowledgments. So that if they ſhall prove Rebels or Apoſtates after ſuch ſolemn Dedications of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unto God, after ſo deliberate a choice of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and renewing their Baptiſmal Covenant; the Font in which they were once regenerated will call them perjur'd, the very Rayles at which they are to kneel, will bring in evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt them, and their own Conſciences without the neceſſity of another Judge will at laſt condemn them. But if to all the preſuppoſed qualifications they ſhall adde a good aſſurance, and humbly addreſs themſelves to the chief Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Church, that by their <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>impoſitions of hands,</hi> they may be confirm'd in their Faith, directed in their Manners, and enabled to perform ſuch worthy reſolutions, they need not queſtion but <hi>according to their faith ſo it ſhall be unto them.</hi> And this brings me to the ſecond General of the Text, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The wonderful Effects or Conſequents of this duty.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Gen.</note> 
               <hi>And they received the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before I treat of this, I think it not altogether unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable to obviate an Objection, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What need is there of all this adoe? Does not the Church of <hi>England</hi> teach that we receive the holy Ghoſt at our Baptiſm, that we are then <hi>made members of Chriſt, Children of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102105:14"/>God, and inheritors of the Kingdom of Heaven?</hi> 'Tis true, we were at that time partakers of the holy Ghoſt, and entituled to all thoſe priviledges; but the gifts of the Spirit at that time imparted, were ſuitable to the ſtate and capacity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we then ſtood; remiſſion of ſins, and the promiſe of the further graces of Gods Spirit; an actual incorporation into Chriſts Church, and a title to the Kingdom of Heaven, was as much as at that time was neceſſary, eſpecially to Baptized Infants. The <hi>Samaritans</hi> here in the Text had undoubtedly the holy Ghoſt communicated unto them, and yet though they were adult perſons, it was thought neceſſary for them to receive from the Apoſtles <hi>Impoſition of hands,</hi> and by that a more abundant meaſure of the holy Ghoſt. Their former ſins, whether original or actual, were then remitted, and an aſſurance given them if they dy'd in that ſtate, that eternal happineſs ſhould be their portion; but here ſtrength is given them againſt future temptations, and their former title upon perſeverance fully ratifyed and confirm'd. And this is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to what <hi>Melciades</hi> an excellent Biſhop (though of <hi>Rome</hi>) in the beginning of the fourth Century hath taught us,<note place="margin">Ep. decret. ad Ep. Hiſp</note> who in his Decretal Epiſtle to the Biſhops of <hi>Spain,</hi> (the former part whereof does indeed ſavour of arrogance, and being no way ſuitable to the modeſty of that Age, may be ſuppoſed ſpurious; but the latter part of it being agreeable to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Doctrine, may be owned as genuine, and that) tells us; <hi>Spiritus ſanctus qui ſuper aquas baptiſmi ſalutifero deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit illapſu, in fonte plenitudinem tribuit ad innocentiam, in confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matione augmentum praeſtat ad gratiam; &amp; quia in hoc mundo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta atate victuris inter inviſibiles hoſtes &amp; pericula gradiendum eſt, in baptiſinate regeneramur ad vitam, poſt baptiſmum confirmamur ad pugnam.</hi> For, ſays he, <hi>As he that is by his General admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Souldier, is not onely ſign'd with a Military mark or badge, but is furniſht with all neceſſary armour, ſo this benediction is an arming of the Baptized. Dediſti militem,</hi> ſays he, <hi>da ei adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta militiae. To what purpoſe,</hi> ſays that good Biſhop, <hi>does a Father bequeath a great eſtate to his Son, niſi providere ſtudeat &amp; Tutorem, unleſs he likewiſe provides a Tutor or Guardian for him?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:102105:14"/>
            <p>I will not ſay, with ſome, that at this time a Guardian-Angel is allotted to each perſon here confirmed; I heartily wiſh it were ſo, but I have no convincing reaſon to conclude it: for ſhould we poſitively aſſert what ever we think expedient, we ſhould ſoon erect an infallible Perſon or Society to ſecure our ſelves from all material errours. However, this I may ſafely aſſert, with that holy Biſhop and Martyr afore-cited, <hi>Paracletus regeneratis in Chriſto Cuſtos &amp; Conſolator &amp; Tutor eſt, The Holy Spirit is appointed to ſuch perſons a Keeper, a Comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and a Guardian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us then, in purſuance of the ſecond General, inquire into the great and ſtupendious effects of this holy Office.</p>
            <p n="1">I. And what they were upon the firſt miniſtration of it particularly here in the Text. Some are of opinion that the holy Ghoſt upon the Apoſtles <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>laying on of hands,</hi> did viſibly deſcend upon the confirmed Chriſtians, as he did on our Saviour after his Baptiſm, and upon the Apoſtles on the day of <hi>Pentecoſt:</hi> others think it ſufficient, that upon the Apoſtles miniſtration of this Office, the gifts of the holy Spirit were convey'd unto them. Thus St. <hi>Stephen</hi> was ſaid to be <hi>full of the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The gifts that were convey'd were of two ſorts; ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and extraordinary. The extraordinary were ſuch as the infancy of the Church did then neceſſarily require, ſuch were working of Miracles, ſpeaking ſtrange Languages, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying of future events, and the like; which gifts as many of the preſent <hi>Samaritans</hi> were endowed with, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles thought good to ſet apart and conſecrate to the holy Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry. Theſe were the <hi>gratiae gratis datae,</hi> which at that time qualified them for the better diſcharge of their duty; very proper to create Faith in the hearts of men, and to gain the Goſpel a ready entertainment.</p>
            <p>Some that would vilifie this holy Office as it is now admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, pretend that none but ſuch extraordinary gifts were at this time conferr'd, and that for the conſtituting of a Church, and enabling them to propagate the Faith. But how weak and frivolous this aſſertion is, appears from the number of theſe confirmed <hi>Samaritans,</hi> who in all probability were all that <hi>believed and were baptized,</hi> and thoſe, <hi>v.</hi> 6. were <hi>the people
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:102105:15"/>with one accord; from the leaſt to the greateſt,</hi> v. 10. <hi>both men and women,</hi> v. 12. Now is it likely that a whole City, which according to its name, was not onely for ſtatelineſs of Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but multitude of inhabitants auguſt and venerable, ſhould be deſtined and ſet apart by the Apoſtles to the holy Miniſtry? What kind of Church were they likely to found at <hi>Samaria,</hi> where like a <hi>Dover</hi>-court all ſhould be ſpeakers and no hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, eſpecially where ſo many women were permitted to tat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle? what a uniform body was this likely to be, which ſhould be made up of Eyes, and Tongues, and Hands, and no other Members to ſecure it from being monſtrous? whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, <hi>The body is not one member, but many;</hi> and <hi>the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit withal.</hi> The holy oyntment that was poured on <hi>Aarons head, ran down his beard,</hi> even <hi>to the skirts of his cloathing;</hi> and theſe great effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Spirit were extended, though not in the ſame, yet in a ſufficient meaſure, to the meaneſt of Chriſts members. In <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. we read of <hi>three thouſand ſouls</hi> converted in one day; and in <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.31. we find that <hi>the place was ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken where they were aſſembled together, and they were all filled with the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Here was an extraordinary confirmation, and yet no extraordinary giſts (as we read of) beſtowed: all that is recorded of the effects of this holy Spirits deſcent is this, that <hi>they ſpake the word of God with boldneſs;</hi> that they were endowed with a true Chriſtian courage and magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to profeſs the Goſpel, nowithſtanding the greateſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragements they met with. 'Tis not unlikely but that in anſwer to their Prayers, <hi>v.</hi> 30. God ſtretched forth his hand to heal, <hi>and ſigns and wonders were done by the Name of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly child Jeſus:</hi> but that any ſuch new gifts were then beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, we have no ground from Scripture to affirm; and that ſo many thouſands ſhould be miraculouſly impowr'd to preach the Goſpel in our modern ſenſe, we have no reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve.</p>
            <p>Beſides thoſe extraordinary Gifts beſtowed upon particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons for ſpecial ends and purpoſes, there were the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and internal Gifts of the Holy Spirit, the <hi>Gratiae gratos facientes,</hi> that were common unto them all, and did render them acceptable unto God. Such were the inlightning of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102105:15"/>their minds, the inflaming of their affections, the endowing them with meekneſs and patience, with courage and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; the inward aſſiſtances of this Spirit, by which their Faith was ſtrengthned, their Hope confirm'd, their Charity enlarg'd, and all their good deſires became vertuous habits, and all their holy reſolutions arm'd with ſtrength for their performance.</p>
            <p>The former ſort of Gifts were of a temporary nature, to continue no longer than the infancy of the Church then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd; they were <hi>ſigna tempori opportuna,</hi> adapted to its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent neceſſities; but the ſecond ſort of Gifts are proper to all Ages, and therefore to continue till the diſſolution of the World; according to that of St. <hi>Chryſ.</hi> in his 13th Hom. on St. <hi>Mat.</hi> thus engliſhed by a Reverend and Learned Prelate of our Church:<note place="margin">Biſh. <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi>'s Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. p. 311</note> 
               <hi>In the beginning of ſpiritual and marvellous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, outward ſignes appeared to confirm the new-preached Faith; but now that the Faith is ſufficiently confirm'd, although ſuch Miracles be not wrought, yet we receive thoſe inward Graces and Vertues which were ſignified and demonſtrated by thoſe ſignes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now thoſe Signes were the Gifts by which <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was at firſt detected at <hi>Samaria,</hi> and at laſt baffled at <hi>Rome;</hi> by theſe the <hi>Wiſe men</hi> and the <hi>Scribes</hi> were ſilenc'd, the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenian Philoſophers</hi> confounded, and the <hi>honeſt-hearted</hi> both <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> converted. This was <hi>the demonſtration of Spirit and of Power,</hi> which the Apoſtles and their immediate Succeſſours did exerciſe; and yet <hi>they did not make the comers thereunto perfect.</hi> They were Gifts highly admirable and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious in themſelves, and as deſirable for their effects; and yet, as deſirable as they were, <hi>I can ſhew you,</hi> out of St. <hi>Paul, a more excellent way,</hi> and that is the ſecond thing propos'd, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. That the conſequents of it now upon its preſent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration by Epiſcopal, are altogether as valuable as thoſe were that heretofore proceeded from Apoſtolical hands. The ſpeaking ſtrange Languages was a gift highly advantageous to the Church in general, but did not ſanctifie the heart, or create any inward Grace in him that had it: <hi>Though I ſpeak with the tongues of men and angels, and have not charity, I am
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:102105:16"/>become as ſounding Braſs, or as a tinkling Cymbal.</hi> The working of Miracles was proper to produce Reverence in the Behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and to command their aſſent to what ſhould be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; but <hi>though I have all faith, ſo that I could remove moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and have no charity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Con. 13.1, 2.</note> ſays St. <hi>Paul, I am nothing.</hi> Charity is <hi>the Bond of Perfectneſs,</hi> the height and eminency of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Vertues; 'tis that which actuates and invigorates all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Graces, without which Faith would be dead, and Hope would be preſumptuous. This intirely unites us unto God, and makes us love our Neighbour as our ſelves. This fixes our reſolutions, and arms us againſt all manner of Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. This keeps us low and Infantlike under the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous ſucceſſes, and buoys up our ſouls from under the hardeſt preſſures. This makes us humble and condeſcending to our Inferiours, courteous and affable to our Equals, lowly and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive (notwithſtanding the greateſt diſappointments we meet with) to our Superiours. Finally to conclude, this is the Holy Ghoſt in the Text, I mean the complement and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of all his Graces that the perſons now to be confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are to be filled with.</p>
            <p>The promiſe of the Holy Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Acts 2.39.</note> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> told the Jews, was <hi>unto them and to their children, and to all that are afar off,</hi> afar off not onely in diſtance of place, but in diſtance of time and relation; and this promiſe, though not of miraculous Gifts, yet of what infinitely outweighs them, the internal ſanctifying Graces of his Spirit, the fruits whereof are <hi>Love, Joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſs, Goodneſs, Faith, Meekneſs, Temperance:</hi> that very Promiſe will on this day be perform'd, and theſe Graces will now be communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if they themſelves do not put a bar, and hinder the effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of this holy Office. And that you may be confirm'd in the belief of this great truth, let me requeſt you to conſider well the third thing propos'd, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. That the ſeeming diſproportion betwixt the outward means and the inward effects, ought not to prejudice any conſiderative perſon againſt the power and efficacy of this Office.</p>
            <p>Will ſome ſay, How is it poſſible that upon ſo ſlight an action as laying on of hands, and the Biſhops Prayers, ſo
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:102105:16"/>much ſtrength againſt all Temptations, ſo much ability to perform all acceptable Duties, ſhould be conveyed unto us? 'Tis true, the meanneſs and ſimplicity of the Ceremony is apt to ſcandalize him who underſtands not the invincible power of God, which oftentimes effects great and ſtupendious Works by light and improbable means; here is nothing (as in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) of pomp and ſolemnity to attract your eyes and raiſe your admiration, nothing but what the holy Apoſtles did practiſe, and that in a very plain yet come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dreſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Father,</hi> ſaid the Servant of <hi>Naaman, if the Prophet had bid thee do ſome great thing, wouldſt thou not have done it? how much rather when he ſaith unto thee, Waſh and be clean?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diſpute not then the poſſibility or manner of its convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, but ſince thou haſt as much need of the Holy Spirit in thy capacity as the primitive Chriſtians had in theirs, fully perſwade thy ſelf that he will not be wanting to thy devout deſires, but as readily aſſiſt thee as he did them; and will no more ſcorn to be invited down now, than heretofore he hath been by Prayer and Impoſition of Hands: For if this Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction be of any force, we may upon equal grounds be ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz'd at the two great Sacraments; the viſible ſignes whereof are altogether as mean, and in themſelves improbable. <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil adeo eſt,</hi> ſays <hi>Tertullian, quod tam obduret mentes hominum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Baptiſ.</note> 
               <hi>quam ſimplicitas divinorum operum quae in actu videtur, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificentia quae in effectu repromittitur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others may again object, that if Miracles did now as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore attend this Office, they ſhould then have reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that great and valuable are the inward effects of it; but ſince thoſe are ceas'd, they ſee not why this Office ſhould not ceaſe with them.</p>
            <p>But in anſwer to this, we muſt know that Miracles were not of the eſſence of this holy Office; for if they had, they would have been eſſential to other Offices which they did ſometimes attend upon. The <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> we find <hi>in a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble manner deſcended upon our Saviour</hi> at his baptiſm;<note place="margin">S. Mat. 3.16</note> and yet the Holy Ghoſts <hi>viſible deſcent</hi> never was lookt upon as eſſential to that Sacrament. When St. <hi>Peter</hi> preacht the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:102105:17"/>to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his Companions, we are told that <hi>while</hi> Peter <hi>yet ſpake thoſe words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 10.44, 46.</note> 
               <hi>the Holy Ghoſt fell on all them which heard the Word; for they heard them ſpeak with tongues, and magnifie God;</hi> and yet the Gift of <hi>Languages</hi> never was ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd to be of the eſſence of Preaching. So that we may with equal reaſon be ſcandaliz'd at thoſe two great Offices, and pretend that the internal Gifts of Gods Spirit do not follow the performance of thoſe Duties, becauſe the external ones are wholly ceas'd.</p>
            <p>Neither ought this to ſcandalize any, That they do not meet with ſenſible alterations, violent motions, ſtrong con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions and tremblings: for though ſometimes the Spirit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtrong convictions may produce ſuch effects, yet here where a due preparation is ſuppos'd, and not a diſpoſſeſſing of Satan, but ſtrength againſt him is wrought, ſuch a violent commotion of the Spirits cannot be expected. But the Holy Ghoſt comes here in a <hi>ſoft voice,</hi> works gently and mildly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rational and intellectual parts of man, and by degrees moulds and faſhions him into the <hi>perfect ſtature</hi> of the Sons of God. As we are not ſenſible of our natural growth, how every day new acceſſions are made to the ſeveral parts of our body, and yet that we do grow, our ſenſes do ſufficiently e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince: ſo neither can it reaſonably be expected that we ſhould underſtand the mode of the divine operations, and the way how ſuch vital ſtrength and nouriſhment is convey'd to our Souls; although after a competent progreſs in the ways of Vertue, we may ſafely conclude that we are grown in Grace; <hi>The Spirit of God bearing witneſs with our ſpirit, that we are the Sons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">IV. Behold then the excellency, the uſefulneſs, the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of this great Office, an Office whoſe antiquity bears date with the holy Scriptures; whoſe lawfulneſs the great Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of our Saviour and his Apoſtles (not to ſay any thing of the conſtant and uninterrupted uſage of it in the Church for many Ages) do vindicate; an Office whoſe expedience and neceſſity of continuance, the great ends and purpoſes for which it was inſtituted, <hi>viz.</hi> the conveying the manifold Gifts of Gods Spirit, do ſufficiently evince; an Office always accounted ſo ſacred, that our late <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping Presbyters</hi> never
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:102105:17"/>durſt pretend to the actual exerciſe of it; an Office from which baptized perſons may expect ſuch great and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble advantages as far ſurpaſs whatever the Gift of Tongues could expreſs, or Miracles declare; an Office whoſe good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences nothing can hinder, but the bars and obſtructions that our ſelves do ſet: finally, an Office which in no part of it lies open to any ſolid Objections even from the worſt of Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>To conclude then this our long and (as I am afraid) tireſom Diſcourſe, let all be perſwaded in their ſeveral Spheres to promote the honour of this excellent Work. Old men and maidens, young men and children, of what ſtate or qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity ſoever, let 'em be ready to entertain this bleſſed Spirit, who is now (as it were) hovering over your heads, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to come down into all prepared hearts.</p>
            <p>And you that intend this day to be partakers of this great Myſtery, that deſire this holy <hi>Comforter</hi> to deſcend from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and take poſſeſſion of your hearts; you that earneſtly long for the refreſhing and ſtrengthening Graces of Gods Spirit; you who are now to engage with <hi>Principalities and Powers,</hi> with the deceitful World and your own Luſts, and come hither to be enabled to <hi>fight that good fight,</hi> and to come off Conquerours: Let me requeſt you deeply to imprint up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your thoughts, not onely the excellency of this Duty, with the gracious effects thereof; but eſpecially that ſolemn pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion that you are here to make, the Covenant with God and his Church that you are about to renew, the ſtrict Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations that lie upon you from thence of being pious and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout, juſt and charitable, meek and temperate.</p>
            <p>For if you come prepar'd with ſuch generous Chriſtian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions as theſe, you need not queſtion but the Graces of Gods Spirit will by the mediation of this his principal Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, be conveyed unto you; <hi>for which you have the ſame war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant,</hi> as the judicious <hi>Hooker</hi> obſerves, <hi>which the Patriarchs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hook.</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Pol. lib. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Prophets, Prieſts, Apoſtles, Fathers, and men of God in all Ages have had for ſuch their particular Invocations and Benedictions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Addreſs your ſelves then to the holy Altar with decency, receive the Bleſſing with Faith and Humility, turn not the <hi>Grace</hi> you are this day to receive <hi>into wantonneſs;</hi> but trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:102105:18"/>it up in an honeſt heart, and let the fruits thereof be diſcernable in your lives: then will you ſecure to your ſelves that ſeven-fold Gift of the Spirit which the Biſhop with the Congregation will preſently pray for; <hi>The Spirit of Wiſdom and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, the Spirit of Counſel and Ghoſtly ſtrength, the the Spirit of Knowledge and true Godlineſs, and the Spirit of his boly Fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for us of the Clergy, as we have reaſon to glory in the number of our <hi>Catechumens,</hi> and to magnifie the God of Heaven for this joyful fruit of our labours: So let us be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to continue this good Work that is ſo happily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, and by catechizing and wholſome inſtructions, prepare the younger ſort ſucceſſively for the like Bleſſings. This will engage his Lordſhip to continue his intended kindneſs, in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming as it were to our doors, though to his great charge, to adminiſter this Office; and we ſhall all reap this comfort by it, that <hi>the Children that are yet unborn will ſtand up and call us bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this holy Office may have its deſired effect, that when the Biſhop <hi>lays his hands upon them,</hi> they may be <hi>filled with the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Let us All here aſſembled, at the pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of each Benediction, unanimouſly ſay, <hi>AMEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102105:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
